ILGWU. Local 40 records 5780/035
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Local 40 records
1933-1977
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Local 40
5780/035
3 cubic feet
3 linear ft.
Minutes, reports, correspondence, newsletters.
The collection contains the records of International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 40, Beltmakers Union. Includes minutes of the Executive Board, Membership, Grievance Board, and Committee meetings. Also includes correspondence, agreements, election files, financial reports, strike files, and issues of the local's publication, The Belt Maker.
5490739
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
D. Mordente, October 22, 2003
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, May 20, 2014
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Having no union of their own for the first two decades of the twentieth century, beltmakers in 1918 appealed to the executive board of the Fancy Leather Goods Workers' Union to undertake an organizing drive. Met with enthusiastic response, almost all beltmakers in New York soon joined the union. These organized members demanded union recognition, a forty four hour week and a thirty percent wage increase. A work stoppage in September 1918 forced employers to the negotiating table. Unwilling to agree to a wage increase, a strike on September 3 brought the belt industry to a standstill. An agreement was reached, but soon the large firms began moving their factories outside of the city and of union control. Between 1919 and 1933, beltmakers in New York were left without a union. By the 1930s, the belt industry saw significant increases in workers and production, especially in the field of women's belts. In 1933, there began a series of walkouts and meetings among workers with the intent to organize. A general strike of 900 workers took place on September 13, 1933 and the employers retaliated with hostility. With the aid of the ILGWU, in 1934 there began a series of walkouts, one shop at a time. Employers began signing collective agreements. While Beltmakers' Union Local 40 was chartered in 1934, it was officially installed as a local of the ILGWU in February 1935.
Scope and Contents
The first half of the collection consists of various minutes. There are minutes of the Executive Board, minutes of the Health and Welfare Committee, minutes of the Grievance Board, and minutes of the Retirement Benefits Fund.
The earliest minutes of the Executive Board are handwritten. Later years contain reports from the various committees as well as the manager's report and a report on the local's finances. The Grievance Board minutes consist of cases that came before the Grievance Board, identified by case number, date, individual grievant and a summary.
Posters announce early meetings of the beltmakers, before the union was chartered. Also in the records are the first agreements with employers, election materials for the new local, and the local's publication "The Belt Maker."
Local 40 produced numerous publications on benefits, plans, and shop conditions. There are publications about the benefits of membership and introductory material for new members, a guide to the union, information about union dues, and a constitution and by-laws. Most interesting are the booklets on belts and belt making. There are diagrams illustrating the different styles of belts and how to sew them. One can also find a booklet on the history of beltmakers and Local 40. Publications were printed both in English and Spanish.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780/034: ILGWU. Local 117 minutes 5780/036: ILGWU. Local 22 minutes 5780/037: ILGWU. Locals minutes 5780/037: ILGWU. Locals minutes
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 40.
5490739
- Executive Board Minutes, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Executive Board Minutes [folder 1 of 2], 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Executive Board Minutes [folder 2 of 2], 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Executive Board Minutes [folder 1 of 2], 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Executive Board Minutes [folder 2 of 2], 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Executive Board Minutes [folder 1 of 2], 1944-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Executive Board Minutes [folder 2 of 2], 1944-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Executive Board Minutes [folder 1 of 2], 1951-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Executive Board Minutes [folder 2 of 2], 1951-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Executive Board Minutes [folder 1 of 2], 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Executive Board Minutes [folder 2 of 2], 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Health and Welfare Committee Minutes, 1939-1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Health and Welfare Committee Minutes, 1946-1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Health and Welfare Committee Minutes [folder 1 of 2], 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Health and Welfare Committee Minutes [folder 2 of 2], 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Grievance Board Minutes [folder 1 of 2], 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Grievance Board Minutes [folder 2 of 2], 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Grievance Board Minutes, 1945-1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Retirement Benefits Fund Minutes [folder 1 of 2], 1953-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Retirement Benefits Fund Minutes [folder 2 of 2], 1953-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Supplementary Employment Severance Benefits Fund, 1959-1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Local 40 Publications [folder 1 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Local 40 Publications [folder 2 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Membership Committee, 1964-1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Record of Dues and Expenditures (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Local 40 Posters (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Membership Meeting Minutes, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Posters and Pamphlets, 1933-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Memorandum of Agreements, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Election Materials, 1935-1939 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Election of New Administration of the Belt Maker's Union, 1942-1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Election Report, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Financial Statements, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Slote and Klein Strike, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- The Belt Maker Vol.I No.1-Vol.II No.10, 1936-1937 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- The Belt Maker Vol.II No.11-Vol.VI No.22, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- The Belt Maker Vol.III No.24-Vol.VI No.23, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- The Belt Maker Vol.IV No.31-Vol.IV No.42, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- The Belt Maker Vol.III No.43-Vol.VII No.4, 1940-1946 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- The Belt Maker Vol.VIII No.1-Vol.LVII No.4, 1947-1957 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- The Belt Maker Vol.LVIII No.8-Vol.V No.4, 1958-1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)